Guide to the Jules Supervielle Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Jules Supervielle collection
1922-1947
GEN MSS 444
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.2
(1 box)
Contains drafts of various plays and poems, and a printed version of Debarcaderes, which has been annotated by Supervielle; and letters and drafts of letters from Supervielle, including one to Felisberto Hernández.
Other Storage Formats: none
Supervielle, Jules, 1884-1960
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ongoing collection of documents acquired by gift and purchase from various sources. Source information is recorded on the folders. For further information, consult the appropriate curator.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
JULES SUPERVIELLE (1884-1960)
Jules Supervielle, a poet, dramatist, and short-story writer of Basque descent, was born in Montevideo, Uruguay. He died in Paris in 1960.
Scope and Contents
This finding aid encompasses accessions of single manuscripts and small groups of manuscripts and other papers, by or pertaining to Jules Supervielle, acquired by the library from a variety of sources. Materials incorporated into the collection prior to August 1999 have been organized into two series. Series I, Writings, contains drafts of various plays and poems, and a printed version of Débarcadères, which has been annotated by Supervielle. Series II, Letters, contains letters from Supervielle to Isabelle Clarke and Elie Richard, as well as drafts of letters to Felisberto Hernández and an unidentified correspondent.
French drama; French poetry; Hernández, Felisberto, 1902-1964; Supervielle, Jules, 1884-1960
- Writings, 1922, n.d.; Series I; 0.20' (1/2 box)
  - "La belle au bois"
    Related Archival Materials note
    See: Box 1, folder 14
  - Bolivar
    - "Analyse de la pièce," draft, holograph, corrected, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Two untitled drafts, holograph (fragments), n.d. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Débarcadères (Paris: Aux éditions de la revue de l'Amérique latine), printed version, corrected, 1922 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - La fable du monde. "Nocturne en plein jour." "Le corps"
    - [Dans cette grande maison que personne ne connaît...], draft, holograph, corrected (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - [Rien qu'un cri differé qui perce sous le coeur...], draft, holograph, corrected (fragment), n.d. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Le forçat innocent. "Saisir." "Saisir." [Un visage à mon oreille], draft, holograph (fragment), n.d. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Naissances
    - [En songeant à un art poétique], draft, holograph, corrected (fragment), n.d. (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - "Métamorphoses." "Naissance d'un palmier," draft, holograph, corrected (fragment), n.d. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Oublieuse mémoire
    - [Ami silence de minuit], draft, holograph, corrected, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 9)
      Scope and Contents
      Titled: "Ami silence de la nuit."
    - [Eurydice], draft, holograph, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - [Sonnet], draft, holograph, corrected, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - "Tableau 7," draft of play, holograph, corrected, with typescript passages pasted in (fragment), n.d. (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Two unidentified drafts, holograph, corrected, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Letters, 1923-47; Series II; 0.20' (1/2 box)
  - To Isabelle H. Clarke, 1926-47 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Includes poem, holograph, corrected: passage from "La belle au bois." With three envelopes.
  - To Felisberto Hernández, draft, holograph, corrected (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - To Elie Richard, 1923-29 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - To an unidentified correspondent, draft, holograph, corrected (Box 1, Folder 17)